MySQL Commands

Start and Stop mysql server

sudo /etc/init.d/mysql start
kojan:~> sudo /etc/init.d/mysql restart
[sudo] password for chris: 
Stopping MySQL database server: mysqld.
Starting MySQL database server: mysqld.
Checking for corrupt, not cleanly closed and upgrade needing tables..

Using killall to kill mysql processes

# killall mysqld
# ps aux|grep mysql
root     12288  0.0  0.0  3508  448 pts/0    S+   16:23   0:00 grep -i mysql

Start SQL Instance

sudo mysqld_safe --defaults-file=/etc/mysql/my.cnf &
sudo mysqld_safe --defaults-file=/etc/mysql2/my.cnf &

Check Logs

mani@mani-ubuntu:~$ sudo tail -f /var/log/syslog

Permissions

chown -R mysql:mysql *

To login (from unix shell) use -h only if needed.

# [mysql dir]/bin/mysql -h hostname -u root -p

Create a database

mysql> create database [databasename];

List all databases

mysql> show databases;

Switch to a database

mysql> use [db name];

See all tables

mysql> show tables;

Database field formats

mysql> describe [table name];

Delete Database

mysql> drop database [database name];

Delete Table

mysql> drop table [table name];

Show all data in a table

mysql> SELECT * FROM [table name];

Returns the columns and column information pertaining to the designated table.

mysql> show columns from [table name];

Show certain selected rows with the value “whatever”.

mysql> SELECT * FROM [table name] WHERE [field name] = "whatever";

Show all records containing the name “Bob” AND the phone number '3444444'.

mysql> SELECT * FROM [table name] WHERE name = "Bob" AND phone_number = '3444444';

Show all records not containing the name “Bob” AND the phone number '3444444' order by the phone_number field.

mysql> SELECT * FROM [table name] WHERE name != "Bob" AND phone_number = '3444444' order by phone_number;

Show all records starting with the letters 'bob' AND the phone number '3444444'.

mysql> SELECT * FROM [table name] WHERE name like "Bob%" AND phone_number = '3444444';

Show all records starting with the letters 'bob' AND the phone number '3444444' limit to records 1 through 5

mysql> SELECT * FROM [table name] WHERE name like "Bob%" AND phone_number = '3444444' limit 1,5;

Use a regular expression to find records. Use “REGEXP BINARY” to force case-sensitivity. This finds any record beginning with a

mysql> SELECT * FROM [table name] WHERE rec RLIKE "^a";

Show unique records

mysql> SELECT DISTINCT [column name] FROM [table name];

Show selected records sorted in an ascending (asc) or descending (desc).

mysql> SELECT [col1],[col2] FROM [table name] ORDER BY [col2] DESC;

Return number of rows

mysql> SELECT COUNT(*) FROM [table name];

Sum column.

mysql> SELECT SUM(*) FROM [table name];

Join tables on common columns.

mysql> select lookup.illustrationid, lookup.personid,person.birthday from lookup left join person
on lookup.personid=person.personid=statement to join birthday in person table with primary illustration id;

Creating a new user. Login as root. Switch to the MySQL db. Make the user. Update privileges.

# mysql -u root -p
mysql> use mysql;
mysql> INSERT INTO user (Host,User,Password)
VALUES('%','username',PASSWORD('password'));
mysql> flush privileges;

Change a users password from unix shell.

# [mysql dir]/bin/mysqladmin -u username -h hostname.blah.org -p password 'new-password'

Change a users password from MySQL prompt. Login as root. Set the password. Update privileges.

# mysql -u root -p
mysql> SET PASSWORD FOR 'user'@'hostname' =
PASSWORD('passwordhere');
mysql> flush privileges;

Recover a MySQL root password. Stop the MySQL server process. Start again with no grant tables. Login to MySQL as root. Set new password. Exit MySQL and restart MySQL server.

# /etc/init.d/mysql stop
# mysqld_safe --skip-grant-tables &
# mysql -u root
mysql> use mysql;
mysql> update user set password=PASSWORD("newrootpassword")
where User='root';
mysql> flush privileges;
mysql> quit
# /etc/init.d/mysql stop
# /etc/init.d/mysql start

Set a root password if there is on root password.

# mysqladmin -u root password newpassword

Update a root password.

# mysqladmin -u root -p oldpassword newpassword

Allow the user “mani” to connect to the server from localhost using the password “passwd”. Login as root. Switch to the MySQL db. Give privileges. Update privileges.

# mysql -u root -p
mysql> use mysql;
mysql> grant usage on *.* to mani@localhost identified by 'passwd';
mysql> flush privileges;

Give user privilages for a db. Login as root. Switch to the MySQL db. Grant privileges. Update privileges.

# mysql -u root -p
mysql> use mysql;
mysql> INSERT INTO db
(Host,Db,User,Select_priv,Insert_priv,Update_priv,Delete_priv ,Create_priv,Drop_priv) VALUES
('%','databasename','username','Y','Y','Y','Y','Y','N');
mysql> flush privileges;

or

mysql> grant all privileges on databasename.* to
username@localhost;
mysql> flush privileges

To update info already in a table

mysql> UPDATE [table name] SET Select_priv = 'Y',Insert_priv = 'Y',Update_priv = 'Y' where [field name] = 'user';

Delete a row(s) from a table

mysql> DELETE from [table name] where [field name] = 'whatever';

Update database permissions/privilages

mysql> flush privileges;

Delete a column.

mysql> alter table [table name] drop column [column name];

Add a new column to db

mysql> alter table [table name] add column [new column name] varchar (20);

Change column name.

mysql> alter table [table name] change [old column name] [new column name] varchar (50);

Make a unique column so you get no duplicates.

mysql> alter table [table name] add unique ([column name]);

Make a column bigger.

mysql> alter table [table name] modify [column name] VARCHAR(3);

Delete unique from table.

mysql> alter table [table name] drop index [colmn name];

Load a CSV file into a table.

mysql> LOAD DATA INFILE '/tmp/filename.csv' replace INTO TABLE [table name] FIELDS TERMINATED BY ',' LINES TERMINATED BY '\n' (field1,field2,field3);

Dump all databases for backup. Backup file is sql commands to recreate all db's.

# [mysql dir]/bin/mysqldump -u root -ppassword --opt >/tmp/alldatabases.sql

Dump one database for backup.

# [mysql dir]/bin/mysqldump -u username -ppassword --databases databasename >/tmp/databasename.sql

Dump a table from a database.

# [mysql dir]/bin/mysqldump -c -u username -ppassword databasename tablename > /tmp/databasename.tablename.sql

Restore database (or database table) from backup.

# [mysql dir]/bin/mysql -u username -ppassword databasename < /tmp/databasename.sql

Create Table Example 1

mysql> CREATE TABLE [table name] (firstname VARCHAR(20),
middleinitial VARCHAR(3), lastname VARCHAR(35),suffix
VARCHAR(3),officeid VARCHAR(10),userid VARCHAR(15),username
VARCHAR(8),email VARCHAR(35),phone VARCHAR(25), groups
VARCHAR(15),datestamp DATE,timestamp time,pgpemail
VARCHAR(255));

Create Table Example 2

mysql> create table [table name] (personid int(50) not null
auto_increment primary key,firstname varchar(35),middlename
varchar(50),lastnamevarchar(50) default 'bato');

20 MySQL (Mysqladmin) Commands for Database Administration in Linux

1. How to set MySQL Root password?

# mysqladmin -u root password YOURNEWPASSWORD

2. How to Change MySQL Root password?

mysqladmin -u root -p123456 password 'xyz123'

3. How to check MySQL Server is running?

# mysqladmin -u root -p ping

Enter password:
mysqld is alive

4. How to Check which MySQL version I am running?

# mysqladmin -u root -p version

Enter password:
mysqladmin  Ver 8.42 Distrib 5.5.28, for Linux on i686
Copyright (c) 2000, 2012, Oracle and/or its affiliates. All rights reserved.

Oracle is a registered trademark of Oracle Corporation and/or its
affiliates. Other names may be trademarks of their respective
owners.

Server version          5.5.28
Protocol version        10
Connection              Localhost via UNIX socket
UNIX socket             /var/lib/mysql/mysql.sock
Uptime:                 7 days 14 min 45 sec

Threads: 2  Questions: 36002  Slow queries: 0  Opens: 15  Flush tables: 1  Open tables: 8  Queries per second avg: 0.059

5. How to Find out current Status of MySQL server?

# mysqladmin -u root -ptmppassword status

Enter password:
Uptime: 606704  Threads: 2  Questions: 36003  Slow queries: 0  Opens: 15  Flush tables: 1  Open tables: 8  Queries per second avg: 0.059

6. How to check status of all MySQL Server Variable’s and value’s?

# mysqladmin -u root -p extended-status

Enter password:
+------------------------------------------+-------------+
| Variable_name                            | Value       |
+------------------------------------------+-------------+
| Aborted_clients                          | 3           |
| Aborted_connects                         | 3           |
| Binlog_cache_disk_use                    | 0           |
| Binlog_cache_use                         | 0           |
| Binlog_stmt_cache_disk_use               | 0           |
| Binlog_stmt_cache_use                    | 0           |
| Bytes_received                           | 6400357     |
| Bytes_sent                               | 2610105     |
| Com_admin_commands                       | 3           |
| Com_assign_to_keycache                   | 0           |
| Com_alter_db                             | 0           |
| Com_alter_db_upgrade                     | 0           |
| Com_alter_event                          | 0           |
| Com_alter_function                       | 0           |
| Com_alter_procedure                      | 0           |
| Com_alter_server                         | 0           |
| Com_alter_table                          | 0           |
| Com_alter_tablespace                     | 0           |
+------------------------------------------+-------------+

7. How to see all MySQL server Variables and Values?

# mysqladmin  -u root -p variables

Enter password:
+---------------------------------------------------+----------------------------------------------+
| Variable_name                                     | Value                                        |
+---------------------------------------------------+----------------------------------------------+
| auto_increment_increment                          | 1                                            |
| auto_increment_offset                             | 1                                            |
| autocommit                                        | ON                                           |
| automatic_sp_privileges                           | ON                                           |
| back_log                                          | 50                                           |
| basedir                                           | /usr                                         |
| big_tables                                        | OFF                                          |
| binlog_cache_size                                 | 32768                                        |
| binlog_direct_non_transactional_updates           | OFF                                          |
| binlog_format                                     | STATEMENT                                    |
| binlog_stmt_cache_size                            | 32768                                        |
| bulk_insert_buffer_size                           | 8388608                                      |
| character_set_client                              | latin1                                       |
| character_set_connection                          | latin1                                       |
| character_set_database                            | latin1                                       |
| character_set_filesystem                          | binary                                       |
| character_set_results                             | latin1                                       |
| character_set_server                              | latin1                                       |
| character_set_system                              | utf8                                         |
| character_sets_dir                                | /usr/share/mysql/charsets/                   |
| collation_connection                              | latin1_swedish_ci                            |
+---------------------------------------------------+----------------------------------------------+

8. How to check all the running Process of MySQL server?

# mysqladmin -u root -p processlist

Enter password:
+-------+---------+-----------------+---------+---------+------+-------+------------------+
| Id    | User    | Host            | db      | Command | Time | State | Info             |
+-------+---------+-----------------+---------+---------+------+-------+------------------+
| 18001 | rsyslog | localhost:38307 | rsyslog | Sleep   | 5590 |       |                  |
| 18020 | root    | localhost       |         | Query   | 0    |       | show processlist |
+-------+---------+-----------------+---------+---------+------+-------+------------------+

9. How to create a Database in MySQL server?

# mysqladmin -u root -p create databasename

Enter password:

# mysql -u root -p

Enter password:
Welcome to the MySQL monitor.  Commands end with ; or \g.
Your MySQL connection id is 18027
Server version: 5.5.28 MySQL Community Server (GPL) by Remi

Copyright (c) 2000, 2012, Oracle and/or its affiliates. All rights reserved.

Oracle is a registered trademark of Oracle Corporation and/or its
affiliates. Other names may be trademarks of their respective
owners.

Type 'help;' or '\h' for help. Type '\c' to clear the current input statement.

mysql> show databases;
+--------------------+
| Database           |
+--------------------+
| information_schema |
| databasename       |
| mysql              |
| test               |
+--------------------+
8 rows in set (0.01 sec)

mysql>

10. How to drop a Database in MySQL server?

# mysqladmin -u root -p drop databasename

Enter password:
Dropping the database is potentially a very bad thing to do.
Any data stored in the database will be destroyed.

Do you really want to drop the 'databasename' database [y/N] y
Database "databasename" dropped

11. How to reload/refresh MySQL Privileges?

# mysqladmin -u root -p reload;
# mysqladmin -u root -p refresh

12. How to shutdown MySQL server Safely?

mysqladmin -u root -p shutdown

Enter password:

You can also use the following commands to start/stop MySQL server.

# /etc/init.d/mysqld stop
# /etc/init.d/mysqld start

13. Some useful MySQL Flush commands

flush-hosts: Flush all host information from host cache.

flush-tables: Flush all tables.

flush-threads: Flush all threads cache.

flush-logs: Flush all information logs.

flush-privileges: Reload the grant tables (same as reload).

flush-status: Clear status variables.

# mysqladmin -u root -p flush-hosts
# mysqladmin -u root -p flush-tables
# mysqladmin -u root -p flush-threads
# mysqladmin -u root -p flush-logs
# mysqladmin -u root -p flush-privileges
# mysqladmin -u root -p flush-status

14. How to kill Sleeping MySQL Client Process?

# mysqladmin -u root -p processlist

Enter password:
+----+------+-----------+----+---------+------+-------+------------------+
| Id | User | Host      | db | Command | Time | State | Info             |
+----+------+-----------+----+---------+------+-------+------------------+
| 5  | root | localhost |    | Sleep   | 14   |       |					 |
| 8  | root | localhost |    | Query   | 0    |       | show processlist |
+----+------+-----------+----+---------+------+-------+------------------+

# mysqladmin -u root -p kill 5

Enter password:
+----+------+-----------+----+---------+------+-------+------------------+
| Id | User | Host      | db | Command | Time | State | Info             |
+----+------+-----------+----+---------+------+-------+------------------+
| 12 | root | localhost |    | Query   | 0    |       | show processlist |
+----+------+-----------+----+---------+------+-------+------------------+

# mysqladmin -u root -p kill 5,10

15. How to run multiple mysqladmin commands together?

# mysqladmin  -u root -p processlist status version

Enter password:
+----+------+-----------+----+---------+------+-------+------------------+
| Id | User | Host      | db | Command | Time | State | Info             |
+----+------+-----------+----+---------+------+-------+------------------+
| 8  | root | localhost |    | Query   | 0    |       | show processlist |
+----+------+-----------+----+---------+------+-------+------------------+
Uptime: 3801  Threads: 1  Questions: 15  Slow queries: 0  Opens: 15  Flush tables: 1  Open tables: 8  Queries per second avg: 0.003
mysqladmin  Ver 8.42 Distrib 5.5.28, for Linux on i686
Copyright (c) 2000, 2012, Oracle and/or its affiliates. All rights reserved.

Oracle is a registered trademark of Oracle Corporation and/or its
affiliates. Other names may be trademarks of their respective
owners.

Server version          5.5.28
Protocol version        10
Connection              Localhost via UNIX socket
UNIX socket             /var/lib/mysql/mysql.sock
Uptime:                 1 hour 3 min 21 sec

Threads: 1  Questions: 15  Slow queries: 0  Opens: 15  Flush tables: 1  Open tables: 8  Queries per second avg: 0.003

16. How to Connect remote mysql server

# mysqladmin  -h 172.16.25.126 -u root -p

17. How to execute command on remote MySQL server

# mysqladmin  -h 172.16.25.126 -u root -p status

18. How to start/stop MySQL replication on a slave server?

# mysqladmin  -u root -p start-slave
# mysqladmin  -u root -p stop-slave

19. How to store MySQL server Debug Information to logs?

# mysqladmin  -u root -p debug

Enter password:

20. How to view mysqladmin options and usage

# mysqladmin --help

Useful commands: http://crashmag.net/list-of-useful-mysql-commands

Drush Check Database with Website credentials

mani@relentless:/srv/www/VRE/sites/etc.lib.unb.ca.acva.contestedterrain> drush sql-cli

Page Example

page_example.info

   1 name = Page example
   2 description = An example module showing how to define a page to be displayed to the user at a given URL.
   3 package = Example modules
   4 core = 7.x
   5 files[] = page_example.test

page_example.module

   1 <?php
   2 
   3 /**
   4  * @file
   5  * Module file for page_example_module.
   6  */
   7 
   8 /**
   9  * @defgroup page_example Example: Page
  10  * @ingroup examples
  11  * @{
  12  * This example demonstrates how a module can display a page at a given URL.
  13  *
  14  * It's important to understand how the menu system works in order to
  15  * implement your own pages. See the Menu Example module for some insight.
  16  *
  17  * @see menu_example
  18  */
  19 
  20 /**
  21  * Implements hook_help().
  22  *
  23  * Through hook_help(), a module can make documentation available to the user
  24  * for the module as a whole or for specific paths. Where the help appears
  25  * depends on the $path specified.
  26  *
  27  * In the first example below, the help text will appear on the simple page
  28  * defined in hook_menu below in the region designated for help text.
  29  *
  30  * In the second example, the text will be available through the module page as
  31  * a link beside the module or on the admin help page (admin/help) in the list
  32  * of help topics using the name of the module. To specify help in the admin
  33  * section use the module name in the path as in the second case below.
  34  *
  35  * @see hook_help()
  36  */
  37 function page_example_help($path, $arg) {
  38   switch ($path) {
  39     case 'examples/page_example/simple':
  40       // Help text for the simple page registered for this path.
  41       return t('This is help text for the simple page.');
  42 
  43     case 'admin/help#page_example':
  44       // Help text for the admin section, using the module name in the path.
  45       return t('This is help text created in the page example\'s second case.');
  46   }
  47 }
  48 
  49 /**
  50  * Implements hook_permission().
  51  *
  52  * Since the access to our new custom pages will be granted based on
  53  * special permissions, we need to define what those permissions are here.
  54  * This ensures that they are available to enable on the user role
  55  * administration pages.
  56  */
  57 function page_example_permission() {
  58   return array(
  59     'access simple page' => array(
  60       'title' => t('Access simple page'),
  61       'description' => t('Allow users to access simple page'),
  62     ),
  63     'access arguments page' => array(
  64       'title' => t('Access page with arguments'),
  65       'description' => t('Allow users to access page with arguments'),
  66     ),
  67   );
  68 }
  69 
  70 /**
  71  * Implements hook_menu().
  72  *
  73  * Because hook_menu() registers URL paths for items defined by the function, it
  74  * is necessary for modules that create pages. Each item can also specify a
  75  * callback function for a given URL. The menu items returned here provide this
  76  * information to the menu system.
  77  *
  78  * We will define some menus, and their paths will be interpreted as follows:
  79  *
  80  * If the user accesses http://example.com/?q=examples/page_example/simple,
  81  * the menu system will first look for a menu item with that path. In this case
  82  * it will find a match, and execute page_example_simple().
  83  *
  84  * If the user accesses http://example.com/?q=examples/page_example/arguments,
  85  * the menu system will find no explicit match, and will fall back to the
  86  * closest match, 'examples/page_example', executing page_example_description().
  87  *
  88  * If the user accesses
  89  * http://example.com/?q=examples/page_example/arguments/1/2, the menu
  90  * system will first look for examples/page_example/arguments/1/2. Not finding
  91  * a match, it will look for examples/page_example/arguments/1/%. Again not
  92  * finding a match, it will look for examples/page_example/arguments/%/2.
  93  * Yet again not finding a match, it will look for
  94  * examples/page_example/arguments/%/%. This time it finds a match, and so will
  95  * execute page_example_arguments(1, 2). Since the parameters are passed to
  96  * the function after the match, the function can do additional checking or
  97  * make use of them before executing the callback function.
  98  *
  99  * @see hook_menu()
 100  * @see menu_example
 101  */
 102 function page_example_menu() {
 103 
 104   // This is the minimum information you can provide for a menu item. This menu
 105   // item will be created in the default menu, usually Navigation.
 106   $items['examples/page_example'] = array(
 107     'title' => 'Page Example',
 108     'page callback' => 'page_example_description',
 109     'access callback' => TRUE,
 110     'expanded' => TRUE,
 111   );
 112 
 113   $items['examples/page_example/simple'] = array(
 114     'title' => 'Simple - no arguments',
 115     'page callback' => 'page_example_simple',
 116     'access arguments' => array('access simple page'),
 117   );
 118 
 119   // By using the MENU_CALLBACK type, we can register the callback for this
 120   // path without the item appearing in the menu; the admin cannot enable the
 121   // item in the menu, either.
 122   //
 123   // Notice that 'page arguments' is an array of numbers. These will be
 124   // replaced with the corresponding parts of the menu path. In this case a 0
 125   // would be replaced by 'example', a 1 by 'page_example', and a 2 by
 126   // 'arguments.' 3 and 4 will be replaced by whatever the user provides.
 127   // These will be passed as arguments to the page_example_arguments() function.
 128   $items['examples/page_example/arguments/%/%'] = array(
 129     'page callback' => 'page_example_arguments',
 130     'page arguments' => array(3, 4),
 131     'access arguments' => array('access arguments page'),
 132     'type' => MENU_CALLBACK,
 133   );
 134 
 135   return $items;
 136 }
 137 
 138 /**
 139  * Constructs a descriptive page.
 140  *
 141  * Our menu maps this function to the path 'examples/page_example'.
 142  *
 143  */
 144 function page_example_description() {
 145   return array('#markup' => t('<p>The page_example provides two pages, "simple" and "arguments".</p><p>The <a href="@simple_link">simple page</a> just returns a renderable array for display.</p><p>The <a href="@arguments_link">arguments page</a> takes two arguments and displays them, as in @arguments_link</p>', array('@simple_link' => url('examples/page_example/simple', array('absolute' => TRUE)), '@arguments_link' => url('examples/page_example/arguments/23/56', array('absolute' => TRUE)))));
 146 }
 147 
 148 /**
 149  * Constructs a simple page.
 150  *
 151  * The simple page callback, mapped to the path 'examples/page_example/simple'.
 152  *
 153  * Page callbacks return a renderable array with the content area of the page.
 154  * The theme system will later render and surround the content in the
 155  * appropriate blocks, navigation, and styling.
 156  *
 157  * If you do not want to use the theme system (for example for outputting an
 158  * image or XML), you should print the content yourself and not return anything.
 159  */
 160 function page_example_simple() {
 161   return array('#markup' => '<p>' . t('Simple page: The quick brown fox jumps over the lazy dog.') . '</p>');
 162 }
 163 
 164 /**
 165  * A more complex page callback that takes arguments.
 166  *
 167  * This callback is mapped to the path 'examples/page_example/arguments/%/%'.
 168  *
 169  * The % arguments are passed in from the page URL. In our hook_menu
 170  * implementation we instructed the menu system to extract the last two
 171  * parameters of the path and pass them to this function as arguments.
 172  *
 173  * This function also demonstrates a more complex render array in the returned
 174  * values. Instead of just rendering the HTML with a theme('item_list'), the
 175  * list is left unrendered, and a #theme attached to it so that it can be
 176  * rendered as late as possible, giving more parts of the system a chance to
 177  * change it if necessary.
 178  *
 179  * Consult @link http://drupal.org/node/930760 Render Arrays documentation
 180  * @endlink for details.
 181  */
 182 function page_example_arguments($first, $second) {
 183   // Make sure you don't trust the URL to be safe! Always check for exploits.
 184   if (!is_numeric($first) || !is_numeric($second)) {
 185     // We will just show a standard "access denied" page in this case.
 186     drupal_access_denied();
 187     return;  // We actually don't get here.
 188   }
 189 
 190   $list[] = t("First number was @number.", array('@number' => $first));
 191   $list[] = t("Second number was @number.", array('@number' => $second));
 192   $list[] = t('The total was @number.', array('@number' => $first + $second));
 193 
 194   $render_array['page_example_arguments'] = array(
 195     '#theme' => 'item_list',  // The theme function to apply to the #items
 196     '#items' => $list,  // The list itself.
 197     '#title' => t('Argument Information'),
 198   );
 199   return $render_array;
 200 }
 201 /**
 202  * @} End of "defgroup page_example".
 203  */

page_example.test

   1 <?php
   2 
   3 /**
   4  * @file
   5  * Test case for Testing the page example module.
   6  *
   7  * This file contains the test cases to check if module is performing as
   8  * expected.
   9  *
  10  */
  11 class PageExampleTestCase extends DrupalWebTestCase {
  12   protected $web_user;
  13 
  14   public static function getInfo() {
  15     return array(
  16       'name' => 'Page example functionality',
  17       'description' => 'Creates page and render the content based on the arguments passed in the URL.',
  18       'group' => 'Examples',
  19     );
  20   }
  21 
  22   /**
  23    * Enable modules and create user with specific permissions.
  24    */
  25   function setUp() {
  26     parent::setUp('page_example');
  27   }
  28 
  29   /**
  30    * Generates a random string of ASCII numeric characters (values 48 to 57).
  31    *
  32    * @param $length
  33    *   Length of random string to generate .
  34    * @return
  35    *   Randomly generated string.
  36    */
  37   private static function randomNumber($length = 8) {
  38     $str = '';
  39     for ($i = 0; $i < $length; $i++) {
  40       $str .= chr(mt_rand(48, 57));
  41     }
  42     return $str;
  43   }
  44 
  45   /**
  46    * Verify that current user has no access to page.
  47    *
  48    * @param $url
  49    *   URL to verify.
  50    */
  51   function pageExampleVerifyNoAccess($url) {
  52     // Test that page returns 403 Access Denied
  53     $this->drupalGet($url);
  54     $this->assertResponse(403);
  55   }
  56 
  57   /**
  58    * Login user, create an example node, and test blog functionality through the admin and user interfaces.
  59    */
  60   function testPageExampleBasic() {
  61 
  62     // Verify that anonymous user can't access the pages created by
  63     // page_example module
  64     $this->pageExampleVerifyNoAccess('examples/page_example/simple');
  65     $this->pageExampleVerifyNoAccess('examples/page_example/arguments/1/2');
  66 
  67     // Create a regular user and login.
  68     $this->web_user = $this->drupalCreateUser();
  69     $this->drupalLogin($this->web_user);
  70 
  71     // Verify that regular user can't access the pages created by
  72     // page_example module
  73     $this->pageExampleVerifyNoAccess('examples/page_example/simple');
  74     $this->pageExampleVerifyNoAccess('examples/page_example/arguments/1/2');
  75 
  76     // Create a user with permissions to access 'simple' page and login.
  77     $this->web_user = $this->drupalCreateUser(array('access simple page'));
  78     $this->drupalLogin($this->web_user);
  79 
  80     // Verify that user can access simple content
  81     $this->drupalGet('examples/page_example/simple');
  82     $this->assertResponse(200, 'simple content successfully accessed.');
  83     $this->assertText(t('The quick brown fox jumps over the lazy dog.'), 'Simple content successfully verified.');
  84 
  85     // Check if user can't access arguments page
  86     $this->pageExampleVerifyNoAccess('examples/page_example/arguments/1/2');
  87 
  88 
  89 
  90     // Create a user with permissions to access 'simple' page and login.
  91     $this->web_user = $this->drupalCreateUser(array('access arguments page'));
  92     $this->drupalLogin($this->web_user);
  93 
  94     // Verify that user can access simple content
  95     $first = $this->randomNumber(3);
  96     $second = $this->randomNumber(3);
  97     $this->drupalGet('examples/page_example/arguments/' . $first . '/' . $second);
  98     $this->assertResponse(200, 'arguments content successfully accessed.');
  99     // Verify argument usage
 100     $this->assertRaw(t("First number was @number.", array('@number' => $first)), 'arguments first argument successfully verified.');
 101     $this->assertRaw(t("Second number was @number.", array('@number' => $second)), 'arguments second argument successfully verified.');
 102     $this->assertRaw(t('The total was @number.', array('@number' => $first + $second)), 'arguments content successfully verified.');
 103 
 104     // Verify incomplete argument call to arguments content
 105     $this->drupalGet('examples/page_example/arguments/' . $first . '/');
 106     $this->assertText("provides two pages");
 107 
 108     // Verify invalid argument call to arguments content
 109     $this->drupalGet('examples/page_example/arguments/' . $first . '/' . $this->randomString());
 110     $this->assertResponse(403, 'Invalid argument for arguments content successfully verified');
 111 
 112     // Verify invalid argument call to arguments content
 113     $this->drupalGet('examples/page_example/arguments/' . $this->randomString() . '/' . $second);
 114     $this->assertResponse(403, 'Invalid argument for arguments content successfully verified');
 115 
 116     // Check if user can't access simple page
 117     $this->pageExampleVerifyNoAccess('examples/page_example/simple');
 118   }
 119 }